[SPEAKER_00]: Because what you call you, your perspective, your discernment, your recognition, is based on the thing already being there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not the other way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like the you observer that's here, watching it, and then it goes away.
[SPEAKER_00]: The observer is there because of the presence of the mental states, which means, if that mental state goes away, that observer... like, it just... it doesn't apply anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe we could...
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know, like, explore, like, what's the... Like, I heard that quite a number of times, like, you know, like, oh, I have a lot of anger, but I don't have any lust, or I have a lot of, kind of, restlessness, but I don't have any doubt, or things like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, eh, some things that I've been contemplating is to see that, try to see that
[SPEAKER_02]: The relationship between the different hindrances, and it's not about, like, the specificity about one or the other, but it's more about, like, how I choose to act, and how that, kind of, opens the door,
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what is the common ground?
[SPEAKER_00]: In terms of how you experience it, the common ground between experiencing one hindrance, experiencing anger, experiencing anxiety,
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, perhaps we should start out by saying that, as long as you don't act out, can we speak of a hindrance?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, but the thing is, you don't see the full extent of acting out initially.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, practically speaking, your mind is pressuring you to do something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you are not peaceful.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's quite obvious.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to that end, your perspective also is constricted, which is the main... like, you don't see things clearly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the main aspect of the hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you may not be acting out of the hindrance, but you can't tell apart left and right, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know that you're not, like, making it worse by acting, but your mind is basically sorting in doubt or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_03]: And now the question is, what is it that all the five things have in common?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because then you would realize that you can't actually have only doubt and no anger, or only anger and no doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only sensuality and no ill-will or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, practically, just recall one time when you were experiencing... the most recent time that you were experiencing a hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: What was the... the thing that preceded the hindrance, the particular...
[SPEAKER_01]: What are the characteristics of that hindrance that would have been in common to all other times that you also experienced hindrances?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it does involve a loss of perspective.
[SPEAKER_03]: By so being identified, let's say, with a content and not seeing a hindrance as a hindrance, that's when you're hindered.
[SPEAKER_01]: But is that loss of perspective just a... just because you forgot something that you...
[SPEAKER_01]: Could I just remember?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is that rooted in something deeper than that lack of perspective?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: I guess you're taking something for granted.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not even like you're not...
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not necessarily there for you to recollect.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but if you... of course, taking things for granted is a byproduct of being hindered, but because you... like, from that perspective of where you are now, hindered, you could say, okay, I won't take things for granted anymore, but you'll still feel...
[SPEAKER_01]: the weight of that hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you still won't really... like you... because you would say, okay, let me not take things for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would recall the same ideas that before used to be the insights that you had developed or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, because of the state you're in, it makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, because you're not seeing your
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but is it only that something that you're not seeing, or is it more than that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, the loss of the perspective is due to the previous acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the previous acting out, what is the most immediate result of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Before the loss of perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before in a structural sense, let's say, not in time.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ah, in a structural sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: How does it feel, basically?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's what we all already said.
[SPEAKER_03]: Your mind begins to pressure you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Towards engagement, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, which is always with the contents.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you go along with that, that is the same as losing the perspective.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's pushing towards engagement.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the thing is, like, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: We want to see what is the common ground between all of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, you might say, okay, especially towards this particular engagement, and then you might think, okay, if I just don't do that, I'm not engaging.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it is more general.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is like, from that point of view, any engagement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what you want to see.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you see that pressure as such,
[SPEAKER_00]: Before it even becomes a specific engagement, then you can see that that's what the common ground is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's how you would fail to actually deal with the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like you think in terms of, okay, sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, okay, it's pressuring towards engagement there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as long as I don't do...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't go there,
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not engaging.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you could be doing a million other things, still, out of pressure, and that means that the common ground of the hindrances is being maintained.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Like you have five empty glasses and you're just kind of emptying, moving the contents from one to the other, but you're not actually getting rid of the water.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what you want to see.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the pressure, in that most general sense, mind that is pressured.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's something that everybody has experienced.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Just imagine, even before you started practicing or something, occasions where you were just completely doing whatever you wanted, just, I don't know, partying or careless conversation, unwholesome activities, and then, at the end of it,
[SPEAKER_00]: You find yourself doing things, saying things, that afterwards you regret.
[SPEAKER_01]: But at the time, it didn't feel... you didn't see any problem with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you might even have, like, shouted at somebody, said something very mean to them, and then you go, and afterwards, you regain perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: You say, oh, sorry for what I did.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was actually stupid.
[SPEAKER_01]: But at the time, you didn't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the... Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you were caught up in that pressure in the moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the... that's the practical way to understand how, when the suttas say,
[SPEAKER_00]: A mind that is pressured by hindrances doesn't see what's for its own benefit, doesn't see what's for the benefit of others, or for the benefit of both.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not in some kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Mystical sense, like it doesn't see reality as it really is or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's... it's... it's the... it's just... oh, this thing that I'm doing is actually harmful for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that simple.
[SPEAKER_00]: And... and it extends to... to... if you take the hindrance in the most fundamental sense, because craving as a whole, appropriation as a whole,
[SPEAKER_01]: Greed, aversion and delusion as a whole, are things that you also do, which are not in your benefit, which are not in the benefit of others, and not in the benefit of both.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by being pressured by hindrances, you wouldn't... because of being pressured by hindrances, you don't see yourself
[SPEAKER_01]: Taking things as mine, being, you know, involved with the aggregates, involved with the sense bases, on that most, kind of, acute level.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, that's why then, you can't... it's not a matter of choice, to like, oh, just try to understand these things, by kind of figuring them out, without
[SPEAKER_00]: First, purifying my conduct, because that's what this is to say, leads to the five hindrances, is misconduct by body, speech, and mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And misconduct not in a sense of, like, some external moralistic sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just anything that's rooted in greed, aversion, and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything that's going to make your mind wild.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, like, you take a child or something, and you just let it do whatever it wants to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every little desire that comes up, you allow it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, afterwards, try to explain to him that doing his homework is good for him.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not going to work.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to look at it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not even like...
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the domain where logic or kind of reasoning has a very limited impact.
[SPEAKER_00]: At best, the reasoning could kind of remind you of like, okay, I have to restrain myself and stop feeding this, so that eventually it will calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you have to actually recognize, well, I created this now and
[SPEAKER_00]: First of all, my first concern shouldn't be like, in the moment, just push it away as quickly as possible, because that's, again, still going to be acting out of hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... now it's like, I need to stop making it worse, and then, basically, keep in mind that the perspective will only really return when that pressure dissipates, if I don't act out of it for long enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... it's eh... it's eh... that's what the training is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it takes place on different levels of subtlety.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, what I mentioned before was like a very coarse example where you would be actually doing things with your body or saying things.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're keeping the precepts, they wouldn't go that far.
[SPEAKER_00]: But still, there's plenty of room for you to basically become careless and do things that... not seeing at that time... See, because that's a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, when you are not under a hindrance,
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't see... you don't have the foresight to see where you're going to end up.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you keep going in that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because right now, it doesn't hurt that much.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind isn't too...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you think, oh, well, I'll handle it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It'll be fine.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a little bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just for this moment, I'll just do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll just give in to this pressure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, because you might actually be capable of handling it, but you don't see how you are already in the background agitating your mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, at some point, it begins to bite you and then it's too late.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, you can handle it right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind... or at least so you think.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see, if you were able to handle it, then why did you do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were able to handle the pressure, if you were...
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, a quantumist words, and you were not moved by it, then why did you give in?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize, it's actually just a kind of secondary... you don't even see your mind, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, you would see, oh, wait.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you wouldn't be able to overlook that direct relationship of, like, pretty much taming yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: to this wild beast.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you know, nobody's gonna come to save you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's... it's... that's why what matters most is like, yeah, inevitably you will get caught up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You... you won't... maybe sometimes not even recognize, like, oh, I was actually being careless there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you find yourself now with a pressuring state of mind of doubt or aversion or ill-will, you don't want to just find a cure for it in the moment, which is what most people tend to think the practice about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just use method techniques to put out the fire that I created through my own behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, I delight in, like, just having the perfect fire extinguisher
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what you actually want to think about is like...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so, I ended up with this pressuring state of mind of doubts...
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever, sad mind, depressed mind, and...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, let's say, it will obviously have to go away at some point, because these things are impermanent, unless you keep feeding them somehow.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, then you want to actually question yourself, okay, but why did this happen?
[SPEAKER_01]: And ten times out of ten, you will see there was a pattern there of things that you were doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It didn't happen by accident.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can you... when you are pressured by a hindrance, how do you know if you can think about certain contexts and themes to re-establish perspective, or if that's not the right direction to go at the time?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're always pressured by a hindrance?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not a... it's not a...
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm trying to discern those patterns that you just said, in the midst of being pressured by the mind, is that what you're saying?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, yeah, but what pattern do you mean?
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, I'm being pressured by this hindrance, and it's because of my past actions.
[SPEAKER_04]: What were those past actions?
[SPEAKER_04]: Do you mean like that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, even that could be helpful, but... Not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_04]: How would you know?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you could also fall into a trap of saying like, okay, so there's a hindrance now.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must not do anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just sit here and grind my teeth and just wait for... and not seeing that that attitude right there could be rooted in the same pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's basically also the answer.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you want to see that...
[SPEAKER_03]: So you want to take into account your intentions for establishing that context again.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what would be the right intention?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, the right... part of the right intention is to not immediately want to get rid of the hindrance now, for example, because then you're quite liable to fall into ill-will.
[SPEAKER_03]: But at the same time, you also want to maintain some perspective, otherwise you fall into doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: So,
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's like training.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you're going to do it wrong quite a few times, but then also, at some point, you will basically see that this perspective is now established again.
[SPEAKER_03]: But this is all mental work, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: We are already assuming that this is not about talking to yourself, or just, oh, shall I go for a walk or not?
[SPEAKER_03]: That's how it starts in the beginning, but at some point...
[SPEAKER_03]: It is... it just becomes completely... because they are fundamentally mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, so... what is it that you would need to recognize in order to do that work on the mental level without, as you said, trying to get rid of the hindrance?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because
[SPEAKER_01]: Often, to most people, it could sound as if you say, OK, don't try to get rid of the hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means like, I just let myself be carried by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you have whatever sensual hindrances or ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: And to you, it might sound like not trying to get rid of the hindrance means like, OK, so I just let that thinking continue and basically just
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but from this point of view, the thinking might already be sort of a by-product.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you do need to recognize something.
[SPEAKER_00]: In order to rightly not try to get rid of the hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, basically, there's a difference between just shirking your responsibility and saying, okay, well, I'm not going to try to get rid of the hindrance, and rightly not trying to get rid of the hindrance in a way that actually started it and eventually brings it to an end.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what would be that recognition that's required there?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I think it's the recognition of the extent of the pressure, when you kind of... when like the line between the pressure and me, quote-unquote, it's kind of clear, like regardless of
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever is coming, you know, like, it cannot pass this point, regardless of what's coming.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if that is very clear, then you can recollect, recollect things that are already present, like the body or whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if this line is not so clear, it's kind of like a sort of grey, you
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you find yourself in the gray and whatever you are doing there, regardless if like trying to recollect the body or maraṇasati or whatever, if this line is not established first, then... You're just spinning.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're just... yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I think that the thing is that to recognize this line first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to recognize
[SPEAKER_00]: First, you have to come to the point where you realize nothing will... nothing bad will actually happen here, unless I do intentionally give in to this pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you would...
[SPEAKER_00]: Practically recognize, like, that you can endure it infinitely, quote-unquote.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, that has to be based on the recognition, like you said, of that line, such that even if it stays there forever, at no point will I actually do something unwholesome on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, of course, the precepts have to be established, but even on the mental level,
[SPEAKER_00]: There is that work to discerning at which point having the mental pressure of, let's say, sensuality or ill-will, at what point that becomes you thinking out of sensuality and in a way which the Buddha said you should never do.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said like... and that's the confusion that often... like when we talk about, oh, we have to endure the sensuality, the mental state of sensuality, the mental state of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then people would quote the sutta saying, where the Buddha says, oh, but as soon as a thought of sensuality, or a thought of ill will, or a thought of cruelty arises, you should obliterate it, eradicate it, and bring it to an end.
[SPEAKER_01]: But those are two completely different things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because the thoughts are things that you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of your choice to to attend
[SPEAKER_00]: To these mental images, basically, and the pressure, the actual pressure of whatever hindrance it is, that's something that's, even if you wanted to, at best, you could look away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to be there anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, that's the crucial distinction.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to clearly discern, okay, this is the mind of whatever hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the mind of doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is the line where
[SPEAKER_00]: Leaving it be, becomes actually acting out of doubt mentally.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, you can...
[SPEAKER_03]: Restrain those thoughts of doubt, which is then the right endurance of the hindrance of doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and practically speaking, that's really all you need to do, because it's fueled, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a fire
[SPEAKER_00]: The only reason it keeps going is because you have been throwing sticks and whatever, cow dung or things that are suitable for that fire to keep going.
[SPEAKER_00]: But most of the time, really, you don't recognize yourself doing that, which is a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once you recognize it, you see, okay, well,
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if it were to last however long, you wouldn't feel that burden of being, like, lost.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's already a regaining of perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just seeing, like, okay, so it doesn't really matter if it stays, as long as I don't get involved with it and make it worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just stay there.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it helps you to recollect the body or recollect feelings or whichever other thing, you would do it now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maintaining perspective of that line, you wouldn't do it, like, with the same impetus of, like, I'm going to do this so that it... so I can push it away quicker or something, out of impatience, which is still within the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, oh, when is it going to go away?
[SPEAKER_00]: If that question arises, you realize, well, I shouldn't
[SPEAKER_00]: Go in that direction, because that's again going to... Like, why would I worry about that, unless I started to overlook the fact that I'm not actually...
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing unwholesome going to happen here, unless I get involved.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: There will be no reason to worry about how long it's going to last.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, which is again, if you get into that, it's going to become either doubt or restlessness, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and you will realize that question cannot be answered.
[SPEAKER_00]: The question is based on the wrong premise, because you can't watch your experience from the outside and see the one hindrance coming in, and then going away, and then... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like you find yourself, because what you call you, your perspective, your discernment, your recognition, is based on the thing already being there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not the other way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like the you observer that's here, watching it, and then it goes away.
[SPEAKER_00]: The observer is there because of the presence of the mental states, which means, if that mental state goes away, that observer... like, it just... it doesn't apply anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.